<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-10T08:46:48+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">GOURI ANIL</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">| Gouri Anil</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/gouri-anil/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="| Gouri Anil"/><published>2025-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/-gouri-anil</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/gouri-anil/"><![CDATA[<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>          Agree &amp; Join LinkedIn
        
  By clicking Continue to join or sign in, you agree to LinkedIn’s User Agreement, Privacy Policy, and Cookie Policy.

      Gouri Anil reposted this
A big congratulations to the all the finalists at the recently concluded Louisiana State University 3 minute thesis- 3MT (graduate research competition) finals! ✨️👏 We were all impressed by the talent and innovation that was on display. The ability of the PhD candidates to distill complex ideas into compelling stories was truly inspiring.  Congratulations to Melanie Wilson for winning the competition with a calm, passionate, compelling, and flawless narration of her research on "How Lead Exposure Disrupts the Brain's Stress Response." 
</code></pre></div></div> <p>I want to extend my appreciation to our PhD candidates for pushing the boundaries of knowledge and advancing their fields. Your research is a testament to the excellence of our graduate school.</p> <p>Kudos to the Dean of the LSU Pinkie Gordon Lane Graduate School Sibel Bargu and her team, for fostering this environment of academic excellence, and to my fellow judges (Deidre Deculus Robert &amp; Brian Snyder ) for their insight and expertise.</p> <p>To all our finalists Adeleye Blessing, Gouri Anil, Md Imran Hossain, Jayasekara Jayasekara, Jyoti Sharma, Israt Jahan Tama, Ekanayaka Arachchige Uthpala nayomi, we can’t wait to see where your phenomenal research takes you! 💡 #3MT #GraduateResearch #Innovation #LSU #ScholarshipFirst #BuildingTeamsThatWinForLouisiana To view or add a comment, sign in</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>        195 followers
      
                Create your free account or sign in to continue your search
              
          or
        
  By clicking Continue to join or sign in, you agree to LinkedIn’s User Agreement, Privacy Policy, and Cookie Policy.

            New to LinkedIn? Join now
          
                      or
                    
                New to LinkedIn? Join now
              
  By clicking Continue to join or sign in, you agree to LinkedIn’s User Agreement, Privacy Policy, and Cookie Policy.
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sign in or join now to see posts like this one and more.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PhD Student Gouri Anil presents her research on Impacts of SAI on Coral Bleaching at the global Reef Futures Symposium in Mexico – Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) Lab</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/phd-student-gouri-anil-presents-her-research-on-impacts-of-sai-on-coral-bleaching-at-the-global-reef-futures-symposium-in-mexico-biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhD Student Gouri Anil presents her research on Impacts of SAI on Coral Bleaching at the global Reef Futures Symposium in Mexico – Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) Lab"/><published>2025-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/phd-student-gouri-anil-presents-her-research-on-impacts-of-sai-on-coral-bleaching-at-the-global-reef-futures-symposium-in-mexico--biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/phd-student-gouri-anil-presents-her-research-on-impacts-of-sai-on-coral-bleaching-at-the-global-reef-futures-symposium-in-mexico-biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab/"><![CDATA[<p>Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) LabDepartment of Ocean and Coastal Science, Louisiana State UniversityIn December, PhD student Gouri Anil attended the global Reef Futures Symposium in Mexico to present her first chapter results. Reef Futures is the only global symposium focused solely on the interventions and actions necessary to allow coral reefs to thrive into the next century.  Solar Climate Intervention has been suggested as a potential tool to aid emission reductions in achieving temperature targets to mitigate climate change impacts. While climate intervention has potential benefits, it is essential to predict and estimate ecosystem impacts for informed decision making. With her research, Gouri assesses the impacts of Stratospheric Aerosol Injection (SAI) on coral reefs. She used Earth System Model simulation daily Sea Surface Temperature (SST) to project and compare spatial and temporal patterns of bleaching between a future moderate emissions climate scenario with and without intervention using Stratospheric Aerosol Injection. The projections are made for marine ecoregion provinces with coral reefs to inform policymakers and stakeholders about the potential benefits or risks of implementing SAI on a vulnerable ecosystem like coral reefs. Her research shows that using SAI to limit global warming to 1.5°C over the preindustrial period could significantly reduce global coral bleaching in the future.She had the opportunity to share her findings with international researchers as well as collaborators working on related projects. She has previously shared her findings at the Ocean Sciences Meeting 2024 in New Orleans. You must be logged in to post a comment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In December, PhD student Gouri Anil attended the global Reef Futures Symposium in Mexico to present her first chapter results. Reef Futures is the only global symposium focused solely on the interventions and actions necessary to allow coral reefs to thrive into the next century.   Solar Climate Intervention has been suggested as a potential tool…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review article preprint: “Potential impacts of climate interventions on marine ecosystems” – Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) Lab</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2024/review-article-preprint-potential-impacts-of-climate-interventions-on-marine-ecosystems-biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review article preprint: “Potential impacts of climate interventions on marine ecosystems” – Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) Lab"/><published>2024-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2024/review-article-preprint-potential-impacts-of-climate-interventions-on-marine-ecosystems--biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2024/review-article-preprint-potential-impacts-of-climate-interventions-on-marine-ecosystems-biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab/"><![CDATA[<p>Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) LabDepartment of Ocean and Coastal Science, Louisiana State UniversityLab postdoc Kelsey Roberts, PI Cheryl Harrison, and lab member Gouri Anil have a preprint available on Potential impacts of climate interventions on marine ecosystems, invited to Reviews of Geophysics. Here is the abstract:Rising global temperatures pose significant risks to marine ecosystems, biodiversity and fisheries. Recent comprehensive assessments suggest that large-scale mitigation efforts to limit warming are falling short, and all feasible future climate projections, including those that represent optimistic emissions reductions, exceed the Paris Agreement’s 1.5°C or 2º warming targets during this century. While avoiding further CO2 emissions remains the most effective way to prevent environmental destabilization, interest is growing in climate interventions – deliberate, large-scale manipulations of the environment aimed at reducing global warming. These include carbon dioxide removal (CDR) to reduce atmospheric CO2 concentrations over time, and solar radiation modification (SRM), which reflects sunlight to lower surface temperatures but does not address root CO2 causes. The effects of these interventions on marine ecosystems, both direct and in combination with ongoing climate change, remain highly uncertain. Given the ocean’s central role in regulating Earth’s climate and supporting global food security, understanding these potential effects is crucial. This review provides an overview of proposed intervention methodologies for marine CDR and SRM and outlines the potential trade-offs and knowledge gaps associated with their impacts on marine ecosystems. Climate interventions have the potential to reduce warming-driven impacts, but could also alter marine food systems, biodiversity and ecosystem function. Effects will vary by pathway, scale, and regional context. Pathway-specific impact assessments are thus crucial to quantify trade-offs between plausible intervention scenarios as well as to identify their expected impacts on marine ecosystems in order to prioritize scaling efforts for low-risk pathways and avoid high-risk scenarios.Gouri Anil studied the impacts of SAI on aragonite saturation and coral reefs. The figure represents Aragonite saturation state (Ωarag), a key measure of the ocean’s ability to support calcium carbonate structures like coral reefs. In the pre-industrial period, most shallow-water reefs were surrounded by high saturation states (Ωarag &gt; 3.25), which has declined due to increasing ocean acidification. Under Stratospheric Aerosol Injection (SAI), the Ωarag levels are even lower than that under climate change. This is due to the increased absorption of carbon dioxide by cooler oceans. The contour lines represent the extent of ideal aragonite saturation state values and there is a stark difference between the present and the future under both climate change and intervention, with a limited number of reefs existing within the ideal.This paper also uses a schematic that highlights the Climate Intervention Methods and a Communication schematic created by Vanessa van Heerden from Louisiana Sea Grant to enhance communication    You must be logged in to post a comment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lab postdoc Kelsey Roberts, PI Cheryl Harrison, and lab member Gouri Anil have a preprint available on Potential impacts of climate interventions on marine ecosystems, invited to Reviews of Geophysics. Here is the abstract: Rising global temperatures pose significant risks to marine ecosystems, biodiversity and fisheries. Recent comprehensive assessments suggest that large-scale mitigation efforts to…]]></summary></entry></feed>