<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-13T07:06:59+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">GOURI ANIL</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Could Stratospheric Aerosol Injection Help Save Corals from Bleaching? - Eos</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/could-stratospheric-aerosol-injection-help-save-corals-from-bleaching-eos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Could Stratospheric Aerosol Injection Help Save Corals from Bleaching? - Eos"/><published>2025-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/could-stratospheric-aerosol-injection-help-save-corals-from-bleaching---eos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/could-stratospheric-aerosol-injection-help-save-corals-from-bleaching-eos/"><![CDATA[<p>Eos Science News by AGU When exposed to environmental stressors like high ocean temperatures and excessive solar radiation, corals bleach and die. Coral reefs collapse, and their benefits—increased biodiversity, protection from coastal erosion, and local economic activity—also disappear.Some researchers think stratospheric aerosol injection (SAI), one of the most well-studied methods of climate intervention, may help mitigate some of the effects coral bleaching when used in tandem with reductions in greenhouse gas emissions. SAI describes a process in which aerosols such as sulfur dioxide are injected into the stratosphere to reduce incoming solar radiation.Get the most fascinating science news stories of the week in your inbox every Friday.To find out whether SAI could help corals, researchers led by physical oceanographer Gouri Anil of Louisiana State University modeled future heat stress on shallow coral reefs with and without the intervention.Anil and her fellow researchers found that SAI could help many vulnerable reefs survive through 2060, giving researchers and lawmakers time to develop more lasting solutions to mitigate climate change. Anil and the research team will present their results on 15 December at AGU’s Annual Meeting 2025 in New Orleans.Anil’s team calculated the heat stress that shallow equatorial reefs across the globe would experience under a moderate climate change scenario with surface sea temperature data from the United Nations’ World Conservation Monitoring Centre and the Community Earth System Model–Whole Atmosphere Community Climate Model version 6 (CESM-WACCM6).The model used in the study is one of the best suited for this type of climate research, according to Alan Robock, a climatologist at Rutgers University who was not involved in the study. Built with data from volcanic eruptions, CESM2-WACCM6 is able to evaluate SAI as a similar release of sulfur dioxide into the atmosphere.The modeling showed that without any intervention, nearly all the coral reefs studied would experience a fatal amount of heat stress by 2060. Certain coral species and coral reefs in central Polynesia and the tropical east Pacific, which are exposed to the most sunlight, were particularly vulnerable.When the researchers simulated a scenario that included SAI, however, the sustainability of shallow equatorial reefs through 2060 improved. Every year, the models showed only 10% of the reefs’ area would be at risk of bleaching if SAI was implemented beginning in 2035.Though SAI may reduce heat stress on coral reefs, researchers said, it could have consequences that require more research to fully understand.For example, sulfur dioxide can react with water and other substances in the atmosphere to form sulfuric acid aerosols. These aerosols eventually precipitate, Robock said. “It’s going to fall out of the atmosphere to produce acid rain, acid snow.”“What we’re trying to do is get this information out to people who make these decisions so that they know exactly what could happen.”Precipitation also means that regular injections of sulfur dioxide into the stratosphere, likely by specialized planes, would be required to maintain SAI’s cooling effect, Robock explained. “You need to put gas continually into the atmosphere—the amount that would be falling out at steady state.”And while the new model points to SAI contributing to reduced heat stress on coral reefs, it doesn’t consider other factors that could affect their survival, including ocean acidification, according to Anil. The researchers are currently working on models that incorporate variables like this.“What we’re trying to do is not advocate for climate intervention,” Anil said. “What we’re trying to do is get this information out to people who make these decisions so that they know exactly what could happen.”—Albert Chern, Science Writer10 December 2025: This article has been updated to correct the climate intervention method mentioned in the headline.About Eos ENGAGE Awards ContactAdvertise Submit Career Center Sitemap</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[New research indicates a well-studied form of climate intervention might at least buy time for many at-risk reefs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PhD Student Gouri Anil presents her research on Impacts of SAI on Coral Bleaching at the global Reef Futures Symposium in Mexico – Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) Lab</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/phd-student-gouri-anil-presents-her-research-on-impacts-of-sai-on-coral-bleaching-at-the-global-reef-futures-symposium-in-mexico-biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhD Student Gouri Anil presents her research on Impacts of SAI on Coral Bleaching at the global Reef Futures Symposium in Mexico – Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) Lab"/><published>2025-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/phd-student-gouri-anil-presents-her-research-on-impacts-of-sai-on-coral-bleaching-at-the-global-reef-futures-symposium-in-mexico--biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2025/phd-student-gouri-anil-presents-her-research-on-impacts-of-sai-on-coral-bleaching-at-the-global-reef-futures-symposium-in-mexico-biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab/"><![CDATA[<p>Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) LabDepartment of Ocean and Coastal Science, Louisiana State UniversityIn December, PhD student Gouri Anil attended the global Reef Futures Symposium in Mexico to present her first chapter results. Reef Futures is the only global symposium focused solely on the interventions and actions necessary to allow coral reefs to thrive into the next century.  Solar Climate Intervention has been suggested as a potential tool to aid emission reductions in achieving temperature targets to mitigate climate change impacts. While climate intervention has potential benefits, it is essential to predict and estimate ecosystem impacts for informed decision making. With her research, Gouri assesses the impacts of Stratospheric Aerosol Injection (SAI) on coral reefs. She used Earth System Model simulation daily Sea Surface Temperature (SST) to project and compare spatial and temporal patterns of bleaching between a future moderate emissions climate scenario with and without intervention using Stratospheric Aerosol Injection. The projections are made for marine ecoregion provinces with coral reefs to inform policymakers and stakeholders about the potential benefits or risks of implementing SAI on a vulnerable ecosystem like coral reefs. Her research shows that using SAI to limit global warming to 1.5°C over the preindustrial period could significantly reduce global coral bleaching in the future.She had the opportunity to share her findings with international researchers as well as collaborators working on related projects. She has previously shared her findings at the Ocean Sciences Meeting 2024 in New Orleans. You must be logged in to post a comment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In December, PhD student Gouri Anil attended the global Reef Futures Symposium in Mexico to present her first chapter results. Reef Futures is the only global symposium focused solely on the interventions and actions necessary to allow coral reefs to thrive into the next century.   Solar Climate Intervention has been suggested as a potential tool…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review article preprint: “Potential impacts of climate interventions on marine ecosystems” – Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) Lab</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2024/review-article-preprint-potential-impacts-of-climate-interventions-on-marine-ecosystems-biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review article preprint: “Potential impacts of climate interventions on marine ecosystems” – Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) Lab"/><published>2024-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2024/review-article-preprint-potential-impacts-of-climate-interventions-on-marine-ecosystems--biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2024/review-article-preprint-potential-impacts-of-climate-interventions-on-marine-ecosystems-biophysical-ocean-modeling-bom-lab/"><![CDATA[<p>Biophysical Ocean Modeling (BOM) LabDepartment of Ocean and Coastal Science, Louisiana State UniversityLab postdoc Kelsey Roberts, PI Cheryl Harrison, and lab member Gouri Anil have a preprint available on Potential impacts of climate interventions on marine ecosystems, invited to Reviews of Geophysics. Here is the abstract:Rising global temperatures pose significant risks to marine ecosystems, biodiversity and fisheries. Recent comprehensive assessments suggest that large-scale mitigation efforts to limit warming are falling short, and all feasible future climate projections, including those that represent optimistic emissions reductions, exceed the Paris Agreement’s 1.5°C or 2º warming targets during this century. While avoiding further CO2 emissions remains the most effective way to prevent environmental destabilization, interest is growing in climate interventions – deliberate, large-scale manipulations of the environment aimed at reducing global warming. These include carbon dioxide removal (CDR) to reduce atmospheric CO2 concentrations over time, and solar radiation modification (SRM), which reflects sunlight to lower surface temperatures but does not address root CO2 causes. The effects of these interventions on marine ecosystems, both direct and in combination with ongoing climate change, remain highly uncertain. Given the ocean’s central role in regulating Earth’s climate and supporting global food security, understanding these potential effects is crucial. This review provides an overview of proposed intervention methodologies for marine CDR and SRM and outlines the potential trade-offs and knowledge gaps associated with their impacts on marine ecosystems. Climate interventions have the potential to reduce warming-driven impacts, but could also alter marine food systems, biodiversity and ecosystem function. Effects will vary by pathway, scale, and regional context. Pathway-specific impact assessments are thus crucial to quantify trade-offs between plausible intervention scenarios as well as to identify their expected impacts on marine ecosystems in order to prioritize scaling efforts for low-risk pathways and avoid high-risk scenarios.Gouri Anil studied the impacts of SAI on aragonite saturation and coral reefs. The figure represents Aragonite saturation state (Ωarag), a key measure of the ocean’s ability to support calcium carbonate structures like coral reefs. In the pre-industrial period, most shallow-water reefs were surrounded by high saturation states (Ωarag &gt; 3.25), which has declined due to increasing ocean acidification. Under Stratospheric Aerosol Injection (SAI), the Ωarag levels are even lower than that under climate change. This is due to the increased absorption of carbon dioxide by cooler oceans. The contour lines represent the extent of ideal aragonite saturation state values and there is a stark difference between the present and the future under both climate change and intervention, with a limited number of reefs existing within the ideal.This paper also uses a schematic that highlights the Climate Intervention Methods and a Communication schematic created by Vanessa van Heerden from Louisiana Sea Grant to enhance communication    You must be logged in to post a comment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lab postdoc Kelsey Roberts, PI Cheryl Harrison, and lab member Gouri Anil have a preprint available on Potential impacts of climate interventions on marine ecosystems, invited to Reviews of Geophysics. Here is the abstract: Rising global temperatures pose significant risks to marine ecosystems, biodiversity and fisheries. Recent comprehensive assessments suggest that large-scale mitigation efforts to…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marine heat waves may be favouring more cyclones in the Arabian Sea: INCOIS scientists - The Hindu</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2023/marine-heat-waves-may-be-favouring-more-cyclones-in-the-arabian-sea-incois-scientists-the-hindu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marine heat waves may be favouring more cyclones in the Arabian Sea: INCOIS scientists - The Hindu"/><published>2023-06-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2023/marine-heat-waves-may-be-favouring-more-cyclones-in-the-arabian-sea-incois-scientists---the-hindu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2023/marine-heat-waves-may-be-favouring-more-cyclones-in-the-arabian-sea-incois-scientists-the-hindu/"><![CDATA[<p>December 6, 2025e-Paper The View From India Looking at World Affairs from the Indian perspective.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>								First Day First Show
								News and reviews from the world of cinema and streaming.
							
								Today's Cache
								Your download of the top 5 technology stories of the day.
							
								Science For All
								The weekly newsletter from science writers takes the jargon out of science and puts the fun in!
							
								Data Point
								Decoding the headlines with facts, figures, and numbers
							
								Health Matters
								Ramya Kannan writes to you on getting to good health, and staying there
							
								The Hindu On Books
								Books of the week, reviews, excerpts, new titles and features.
							December 6, 2025e-PaperUpdated  - June 19, 2023 07:50 am IST - HYDERABAD
                Within the twin cities, Monda Market and Begumpet with 41.2°C recorded the maximum day temperature on Sunday. 
                                      | Photo Credit: MOHD ARIF
                                  Marine heat waves could have provided a favourable condition for the cyclone ‘Biparjoy’ to form over the Arabian Sea and become a very severe cyclone, say scientists of the Indian National Centre for Ocean Information Systems (INCOIS) under the Ministry of Earth Sciences (MoES).A warmer ocean water column helps build moisture content in the air and thus provides the necessary energy source for cyclonic storms to form over the ocean. When the ocean remains warmer beyond a threshold from the normal condition for a prolonged period, these events are referred to as marine heatwaves. A marine heat wave was prevailing in the eastern Arabian Sea since early May. The sea surface temperature was more than 31° C (1° C warmer than normal), during the entire May and early June this year. Senior scientist Abhisek Chatterjee and his students Gouri Anil, and Lakshmi R. Shenoy investigated the trends and genesis of heat waves and found these events are becoming prolonged and sometimes persistent for the entire pre-monsoon season in the recent decade. Their study showed similar heatwave conditions to be prevailing during the other recent severe cyclones such as ‘Tauktae’ and ‘Nisagra’, which hit the west coast of India and caused extensive damage to property and life.These events suggest that increased cyclogenesis over the Arabian Sea in the recent decade is linked to persistent extreme warm ocean conditions. The sea has been found to be warming at a much more rapid pace among the other tropical basins in recent decades.The research done between 1982–2019 period showed that the frequency of heatwaves increased at a rate of about 1.5–2 events per decade in the northern Arabian Sea and the southeastern Arabian Sea close to the Indian west coast. The increasing trend of heatwave days is mainly evident in the post-2000 era and conspicuous after 2015. As the number of heatwave days has increased significantly over the last two decades, the number of tropical cyclones has also increased over the Arabian Sea. While a multi-fold increase in heat waves was observed from the ‘80s and since the beginning of the satellite record, the years 2010 and 2016 have exhibited the maximum number of heatwave days when more than 75% of days of the pre-monsoon and summer monsoon season experience heatwaves.While this accelerated trend of heatwaves is found to be driven by a rapid rise in the mean Sea Surface Temperature (SST) of the Arabian Sea in the recent decade, these events are also found to be associated with dominant climate modes such as ‘El Nino’.Since El Nino usually also impacts the Indian Summer monsoon rainfall, the drought years over the subcontinent will likely co-occur with heat waves on the oceans. This rapid increase in heatwaves is likely to have an impact on the physio-biogeochemical processes of this basin as well, such as an increase in the harmful algal bloom and coral bleaching in the Arabian Sea, the scientists added. “We have recently launched the marine heatwave advisory services for better understanding and preparedness considering the potential impact of such events, ”said INCOIS Director Srinivasa Kumar Tummala. Funding for the work published in ‘Ocean Science’ was provided from the MoES “Deep Ocean Mission” programme. Published - June 18, 2023 07:34 pm IST
				Copyright© 2025, THG PUBLISHING PVT LTD. or its affiliated companies. All rights reserved.
			BACK TO TOPTerms &amp; conditions  |  Institutional SubscriberComments have to be in English, and in full sentences. They cannot be abusive or personal. Please abide by our community guidelines   for posting your comments. We have migrated to a new commenting platform. If you are already a registered user of The Hindu and logged in, you may continue to engage with our articles. If you do not have an account please register and login to post comments. Users can access their older comments by logging into their accounts on Vuukle.
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Heatwave conditions on Arabian sea is likely to help more cyclones forming over the Arabian Sea, say scientists at INCOIS]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arabian Sea: ‘at Least 20 Marine Heatwave Days In Arabian Sea During Last Decade’ | Kochi News - Times of India</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2022/arabian-sea-at-least-20-marine-heatwave-days-in-arabian-sea-during-last-decade-kochi-news-times-of-india/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arabian Sea: ‘at Least 20 Marine Heatwave Days In Arabian Sea During Last Decade’ | Kochi News - Times of India"/><published>2022-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2022/arabian-sea-at-least-20-marine-heatwave-days-in-arabian-sea-during-last-decade--kochi-news---times-of-india</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2022/arabian-sea-at-least-20-marine-heatwave-days-in-arabian-sea-during-last-decade-kochi-news-times-of-india/"><![CDATA[<p>Sudha Nambudiri reports from the southern state of Kerala. She writes on climate change, science and technology, social issues, and culture.How to make easy dump &amp; dine Tofu Salad for dinnerHow to grow Blueberries in home garden or balcony9 ways to magically improve your communication skills (without any books)10 most beautiful temples in India perfect for weddings10 delicious dishes made with fresh coconutEasy-to-make Bengali-style Macher Chop (Fish Chops)How to make one-pot dry-fruit Veg Pulao10 reasons to drink anjeer water every morning10 baby girl names from Greek and Roman mythologies10 inspiring quotes by Swami Vivekananda that are excellent tips for success</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There have been at least 20 marine heatwave days at an average of 1.5 to 2 events per year in the Arabian Sea in the last decade, according to a rece]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Increasing marine heatwaves in the Arabian Sea impact marine ecosystems</title><link href="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2022/increasing-marine-heatwaves-in-the-arabian-sea-impact-marine-ecosystems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Increasing marine heatwaves in the Arabian Sea impact marine ecosystems"/><published>2022-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2022/increasing-marine-heatwaves-in-the-arabian-sea-impact-marine-ecosystems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gouria98.github.io/blog/2022/increasing-marine-heatwaves-in-the-arabian-sea-impact-marine-ecosystems/"><![CDATA[<p>If you liked this story, share it with other people. The Arabian Sea is experiencing a rapid increase in heatwave days with sea surface temperature extremes in the last decade sometimes stretching out through a season, according to a new study. In the last four decades, between 1982 and 2019, every decade has seen roughly 20 more marine heatwave days, says the study, that used satellite data to highlight the trends of these marine temperature extremes on the west coast of India.The increasing trend of marine heatwave (MHW) days is more noticeable after the year 2000, and is clearly visible after 2015. The accelerated trend of the heatwave days is found to be driven by the rapid rise in the mean sea surface temperature (SST) of the Arabian Sea in the recent decade, the paper highlights.Longer heatwave days are also associated with climate patterns such as El Niño, which is the warm phase of the El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO), a naturally occurring climate phenomenon that involves fluctuating ocean temperatures in the tropical Pacific, coupled with changes in the atmosphere. La Nina is the cooling phase of ENSO. According to the World Meteorological Organisation, all naturally occurring climate events now take place against a background of human-induced climate change which is worsening extreme weather and affecting the water cycle.In the Indian Ocean basin, El Niño influences more than 70 - 80 percent of observed heatwave days through the Indian Ocean Basin Mode, a delayed warming response within the Indian Ocean in response to El Niño, said physical oceanographer Abhisek Chatterjee.“Our analysis shows that the frequency and duration of marine heatwaves exhibit a rapidly increasing trend of roughly 20 days per decade (1.5-2 events per decade) in the northern Arabian Sea and the southeastern Arabian Sea close to the west coast of India. This increase is a multifold increase in MHW days from the 1980s,” study lead author Chatterjee at Indian National Centre for Ocean Information Services (INCOIS), Ministry of Earth Sciences, Hyderabad, India, told Mongabay-India.“We need to predict marine heatwaves and unpack their impacts in the Arabian Sea region including understanding their influence on the local marine ecosystem, the migration of species, and the associated fishery-dependent economy,” said Chatterjee, adding that while the understanding of the origin of MHWs across the globe has advanced rapidly over the last decade, there are not many studies to document these events in the northern Indian Ocean.The study relied on sea surface temperature data from satellite sources to analyse three primary metrics of heatwaves: duration, frequency, and intensity for the period of 1982–2019 (1982 onwards is referred to as the era of satellite observations). After 2000, the number of heatwave days increased significantly, with an average of 10-20 percent days experiencing heatwaves in almost all years. A rapid increase in heatwave days is observed from 2015 onwards with at least 25-50 percent days experiencing heatwaves.The increase in frequency and duration of marine heatwaves is also emphasised in the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change’s Special Report on the Oceans and Cryosphere in a Changing Climate which states that marine heat-related events have increased globally and over the period 1982-2016; they have doubled in frequency and have become longer-lasting, more intense and more extensive. The panel iterates that it is very likely that between 84-90 percent of marine heatwaves that occurred between 2006 and 2015 are attributable to the human-caused temperature increase.Australia-based scientist and lecturer, Alex Sen Gupta, highlights the 2010-2011 Ningaloo Niño off Western Australia that spurred research into marine heatwaves (MHW). Ningaloo Niño led to extensive and sustained loss of kelp habitat, fisheries closures and the invasion of tropical species into temperate waters. Sen Gupta was not associated with the Arabian Sea study.“It was an incredible, massive event and it had really big ecological impacts that were very long-lasting as well. So even though the event occurred in 2010, we’re still seeing its impacts. And that sort of drove this global interest in marine heatwaves. So it’s been rising exponentially since then,” said Sen Gupta at the Climate Change Research Centre, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia.Another iconic heatwave (the most intense and the highest category MHW in the satellite era) event was in 2015. It encapsulated most of the Indian Ocean and coincided with the strong El Niño that year, causing widespread coral bleaching in the Lakshadweep archipelago.“We did a study a few years ago that tells us that over the last century, globally we’ve had about a 54 percent increase in the amount of time that we would consider as a marine heatwave. So if before we had six days a year that was considered a marine heatwave, now we have nine or 10 days a year. And that number is going up rapidly as the mean sea surface temperature is going up rapidly,” said Sen Gupta.In India, researchers also point to a link between recent cyclones in the Arabian Sea and the prolonged marine heatwaves. “We also see that a prolonged marine heatwave in the Arabian Sea is associated with a cyclone. And the cyclone helps the heatwave to decay. Bigger cyclones such as in 2010, in 2020 (cyclone Nisarga) and in 2021, were associated with marine heatwaves that were prolonged,” said Chatterjee.“There is a clear signal between cyclones and marine heatwaves and we need to extract the information and incorporate them in modeling,” corroborates Roxy Mathew Koll at the Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology (IITM), Pune, who was not involved in the present study.Koll and his colleagues showed in a recent study that an increase in marine heatwave events in the northern Indian Ocean affects monsoon rainfall in India. Marine heatwaves over the western Indian Ocean and the Bay of Bengal are causing drying conditions over the central Indian subcontinent. At the same time, the marine heatwaves over the north Bay of Bengal are causing a “significant increase” in the rainfall over south peninsular India.Like Chatterjee at INCOIS, Koll’s research group also used satellite sources between 1982 and 2019. They showed that the western Indian Ocean region experienced the largest increase in marine heatwaves at a rate of about 1.5 events per decade, followed by the north Bay of Bengal at a rate of 0.5 events per decade. The western Indian Ocean experienced 66 events while the Bay of Bengal had 94 events over the last four decades, between 1982 and 2018.In light of the recent evidence, experts have called for “prioritisation” of the prediction of marine heatwaves and monitoring subsurface ocean waters.“We also need to strengthen our in-situ ocean understanding through enhanced ocean observations because while satellite sources capture temperature data, the data captured is an underestimate. Even a two-degree Celsius difference between satellite data and in-situ observations is huge,” Koll said.Marine heatwave predictions and forecasts can come in handy for policymakers, fishery managers and resource managers. “They may be able to do things such as switch to different species, or change when they’re going to harvest their products, or they might – if it’s an oyster farm– take the oysters and put them in different regions. So, in short timescales, we can think of certain management solutions once our predictions become good enough,” added Alex Sen Gupta.“And that’s one of the things that science is trying very hard at moment to do is to try and make our models better. So we can actually either predict individual marine heatwaves or try to give statistical forecasts to say that a marine heatwave is more likely to occur in this season. The other timescale, of course, is the general global warming.”“We need to slow down global warming and reduce greenhouse gas emissions,” Sen Gupta said.Read more: Broaden understanding of marine heatwaves in the Indian Ocean: ExpertsBased on the coverage of satellite data, the years 2010 and 2016 show the longest heatwave days in the Arabian Sea, which were due to the overlap between strong El Niño and the average ocean warming trend, causing high and persistently warm sea surface temperature (SST) across the Arabian Sea. As a case study, the researchers unravelled the year 2010 – the longest observed event since the availability of satellite observations; the heatwave lasted for about 60-70 days.The heatwave started brewing sometime in the last week of March, 2010, in the northern and northeastern parts of the Arabian Sea when the sea surface temperature was hovering around 27-29 degrees Celsius i.e. about 0.5 degrees Celsius more than the threshold. It spread by the third week of April, 2010 and covered the entire northern part of the Arabian Sea. The heatwave intensified by May as the sea warms further. By mid-June, the heatwave waned with the summer monsoon clouds setting in across the Western Ghats of India. The onset of summer monsoon clouds reduced the shortwave radiation, eventually contributing to the decreasing temperature and termination of the heatwave.INCOIS’s Abhisek Chatterjee says longer marine heatwaves could also worsen impacts on corals because of water’s high specific heat capacity. “Once it gets warm, it will not cool fast.”The increased frequency of these events does not allow ecosystems, such as coral reefs, enough time to bounce back. Scientists studying the mass coral bleaching in India’s Lakshadweep archipelago in 2015-2016 El Niño-associated bleaching event, called the damage “heartwrenching.” The El Niño hit the reefs in Lakshadweep before they could completely recover from 2010’s catastrophic El Niño.The cascading impacts of MHWs can last for decades – the loss of fisheries, destruction of kelp forests or seagrass habitats and their natural capacity to store carbon, mass mortalities of wildlife and knock-on economic consequences that already run into billions of U.S. dollars.“For example, the Ningaloo event had a massive effect on the fishery in that year, but it completely devastated the habitat. The kelp habitat up and down the coastline for hundreds of kilometers was destroyed and they haven’t come back since then,” tells Sen Gupta.“You’ve got losses in relatively small regions from tens to up to hundreds of millions of dollars related to a single marine heatwave event,” he said, referring to the research on the global perspective of the socioeconomic impacts of marine heatwaves.In 2015, Kripa Vasant, who contributed to the recent IPCC report on adaptation, was shocked to see a massive drop in phytoplankton density in southeastern Arabian Sea waters off the coast of Kerala along India’s southwest coast. This stretch is home to the Malabar upwelling zone, one of the most important upwelling zones in the world. Upwelling occurs when winds push surface water away from the shore and deeper nutrient-rich water rises to fill the gap.Upwelling encourages the growth of plant life, including phytoplankton. These phytoplankton provide food for fish, marine mammals, seabirds, and other critters. These upwelling zones are good fishing grounds. The Malabar upwelling zone, with its phytoplankton-rich waters, supports a major habitat of the Indian oil sardine, nicknamed ‘family provider’ because of its contribution to Kerala’s coastal economy.“In 2015, there was almost no phytoplankton. This glut was linked to the extreme El Nino event which caused high sea surface temperatures. The combination of low food availability (phytoplankton) with the high sea surface temperatures in the sardine habitat in 2015 was like a ‘drought in the ocean’. This ‘oceanic drought’ contributed to the drop in sardine fishery that year (estimated to be to the tune of  150 crore rupees), which was already reeling from a decline in the past few years due to over-exploitation. The fishing community was hit very hard,” added Vasant, who was with Central Marine Fisheries Research Institute, Kochi, Kerala and is now Member Secretary, Coastal. Aquaculture Authority, Chennai.Chatterjee says it is important to look at marine heatwaves in the context of mitigation actions associated with impacts of extreme events such as El Niño on land. “During El Niño, you always prepare for a weaker monsoon (because El Niño is known to suppress monsoon rainfall) because the El Niño forecast is usually given a season in advance. So, we actually have a mitigation policy on how to handle the farming situation, but we don’t consider it in terms of the impacts on marine food sources.”“The marine food system is also linked to India’s economy and we need to look at marine heat extremes also in that context,” he added.Vasant agrees that the prediction of marine heatwaves will help the fisher community prepare for the worst and such extreme events at the sea need to recognised as disasters. “When fishery is hit due to ocean extremes, the community doesn’t receive relief as ‘drought in the sea’ is not recognised,” she added. Banner image: Sunset at a Goa beach, Arabian Sea. The Arabian Sea is experiencing a rapid increase in heatwave days with sea surface temperature extremes in the last decade. Photo by Kai Müller/Pixabay.If the Green Revolution rode on the strength of chemicals derived mainly from fossil fuels, now there is a shift in the thinking on how agriculture is being done in India, with a thrust on growing indigenous crop varieties and following natural farming practices. In the industrial sector, with initiatives such as ‘Make in India’, […] © 2025 Copyright Conservation news. Mongabay is a U.S.-based non-profit conservation and environmental science news platform. Our EIN or tax ID is 45-3714703.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[India's environmental science and conservation news]]></summary></entry></feed>